[music]
[music] signal
and speak.
>> Dr. Barry Chaken is not just a physician
leader. He's a strategic and a longtime
advocate for meaningful healthc care
change with more than 25 years of
experience in clinical transformation
health IT and public health. He's worked
across payer provider and policy
domains. Barry served as chief medical
officer under m multiple health tech
companies advised the federal government
on pandemic preparedness and is a past
board chair of HIMS. He also is the
founder of DocsNetwork, a consultancy
focused on clinical innovation and
patient safety. But beyond his resume,
Barry brings a steady voice on the
ethical use of technology, the culture
of care,
and the human moments that often get
lost in the machinery of healthcare
systems. In this conversation, we talk
about what it takes to lead with
integrity, how to challenge orthodoxy in
times of change, and why he still
believes healthc care is a calling. Dr.
Barry Chaken, welcome to the Signal
Room.
>> Thank you so much, Chris. I really
appreciate that introduction.
>> Well, it it's an honor to have you. I've
known you for a number of years and it's
just exciting to be able to launch the
Signal Room with a with a good friend
and a visionary at the same time. So,
again, thank you and welcome.
Let's just jump right into it. I'm kind
of excited you just to talk about some
of the things you've been working on. Uh
very timely and relevant for the the
world we're living in and all the
buzzwords that are out there. I think
you're going to bring some some real
real life uh humanity to it. It's not
just the technology discussion. So,
let's just jump right in. Dr. Shaken,
your career has spanned clinical
practice, public health, and technology.
I want to ask you about your book. What
inspired you to write Future Healthcare
2050 at this particular moment? Well, I
have to tell you, I have to go back to
the time that I was in AIS officer and
it was one of the first visits that I
did to the CDC
uh in my training and I saw this IBM PC
sitting there and I was like, "Oh, tech
is really interesting and that actually
got me interested in technology and I've
been using it my entire life." So what
it was about two years ago chat tpt came
out where you could actually without
being a programmer interact with it and
I said let me learn about this new
technology and that got me very much
interested in artificial intelligence
and again not from the place where I was
a data scientist and I was worried about
JSONs and Pythons and coding but about
how to use artificial intelligence in a
way that it could be helpful in your
personal life and then in your Burke and
then of course in healthcare and that
inspired me to say let me see what I
could do to talk about health care and
AI as it started to become more
mainstream type of technology that
people became familiar with that
inspired me to write the book. I also
and throughout the book I put this
concept in which is the idea of trust. I
wanted to make sure understanding some
of the risks of AI back in the beginning
that have continued to this day. We have
to make sure that if we're going to use
artificial intelligence, it needs to be
done in a way that really is focuses on
on health care, on the patient, and on
the benefits to society. And that really
inspired me to write the book.
>> Yeah. So, definitely more on more to do
on the human interaction side than than
on the tech. I think we've been excited
about technology forever and we honestly
we've not done ourselves a lot of favors
in recent years with our focus on that.
So
let's talk a little bit about some of
the things that led up to that. Uh you
one point coined the term RHIT in your
previous book that you've written. How
does that concept evolve in this new
work especially in light of AI's
acceleration?
>> Well I I use the word revolutionary. It
stands for Revolutionary Health IT
used the word revolutionary because I
wanted to people think of something
completely new different a different
direction a change in how we did things
and just using evolutionary health it
didn't really cut it for me and I wanted
to be people to understand that
information technology tools are just
that they are just tools and if you
don't figure out and plan, how are you
going to utilize them and tie them to
the outcomes and goals that you want?
They're just tools and you can go ahead
and do spend a lot of money, a lot of
time,
>> right?
>> And not only achieve nothing, you might
even make things worse. I learned that
through my experiences working with
electronic health records and of course
uh when I wrote my book of re on
navigating the code. It was about
process redesign, analytics, workflow
redesign and the idea that you need to
go and ch use technology for a
particular goal to achieve a particular
objective and requires you to do not
just use the technology but you design
redesign the things around it to make
sure the technology used in a proper way
that is revolutionary in terms of the
outcomes it delivers.
>> That that's such an important
distinction. I I I it's unfortunate that
we we are so word sensitive but I think
revolutionary is the right word for what
you're describing.
So terms of transformation
in the book you you're exploring how AI
could reshape the patient physician
journey.
What did you what do you think is the
most misunderstood aspect of that
transformation today? My experience in
working with technology has shown me
that people like to get excited about
that new bright shiny object,
>> right? And I understand we all love new
things, right? We love a new pair of
sneakers. We love a new technology we
get to work with,
>> but we always have to be focused on the
objectives and the outcome. There's a
lot of talk today about um using
clinical artificial int artificial
intelligence to achieve a particular
goal or objective. I think that is has
tremendous potential.
But the issue here is we have have a lot
of work to do to achieve that. I think
there's a lot we can do to you further
humanize how we deliver health care
using artificial intelligence by making
the interaction between the caregiver
which is not just the physician but the
nurses physical therapists people do the
blood draw the people who register you
at the clinic make that interaction more
personal and the way it can be done is
AI can can do two things one it can
prepare the caregiver so they can have a
more personal humanistic
interaction with that person by giving
that caregiver information before they
see that patient. And secondarily, the
interaction that the patient has with
the system, even if it's automated, can
be personalized. Whether it means right
>> before you have your surgery, you're
going to have instructions of the things
you need to do to prepare yourself for
that surgery. They can be personalized
to who you are, to the language that you
that you speak, to the level of
education that you have, to the type of
job that you actually you do, and it can
adjust its recommendations and speak to
you in a language that can be more
motivating and comforting for you. The
same way the interaction between the
physician and the patient can be more
humanized in the interaction by the
information given to that physician but
also in the communication written verbal
and otherwise to that patient by
personalizing it around who they are,
what their current diseases may be,
their challenges may be their family
situation. These are things that we
cannot do as humans. It's just too much
to cover. that AI can actually help us
do that.
>> Yeah, I love that you you you bring out
a really important thing that we could
easily lose sight of and you know, yeah,
it the patient experience obviously is
the one of the most important things we
can look at, but it's not only a
physician they are interacting with. Um,
a bad experience at check-in can be just
as much of a problem uh for the patient
as anything else. So, you know, focusing
on the people that are essentially being
their services are being wrapped around
that patient experience. There's just a
lot of opportunities in there. Let's
talk about what what practical solutions
might be in the near term. What AI use
cases that that you think health system
should be focused on and maybe talk a
little bit about one or two that you
believe are overhyped.
>> The overhyped ones are really easy. So,
let's talk about some of the practical
ones. Okay. We know a lot about
physician burnout.
We know about nurse burnout and other
caregiver burnout because of the
documentation. So, let's go back to
where that was. We created these
electronic health records.
>> Why were they created? They were created
to help patients. No, they were not
developed to document patient care. They
were developed so that it would make it
easier for organizations to document
care for the purpose of receiving
reimbursement.
We have a a reimbursement system in the
United States, right? That is
>> dependent upon that documentation. I'm
not going to talk about the pros and
cons of that. There are many arguments
on all sides and all of them are valid.
I'm just talking about the EHR was
developed for documentation. Why was it
done that way? Very simple. Who would
buy a system that didn't optimize
the documentation for reimbursement?
>> Nobody. So, what we tried to do through
meaningful use and other measures by the
government to make it so it was focused
on the health care and the outcomes of
that patient. But reality is we live in
a system whether you're a for-profit or
not for-profit organization.
>> We survive by generating the proper
revenue for our organization to keep it
going. And to be fair, that includes
generating revenue to pay for people who
can't pay for the care.
So that's part of the process. It's not
just generating revenue for the benefit
of senior people or for a board or for
something like that. It's really also to
have surplus money to take care of those
who can't afford to provide care and has
provided essentially free care. So
that's where the revenue piece is.
So I think if we are never going to get
rid of that requirement unless we
completely change our healthare system.
>> So we need to away how can we decrease
that burden. The way we can do it is we
can use AI through ambient listening and
other other processes to make it so the
physician can focus on the patient. Why
do I think this is really important?
It's not just the time that the the
physician can spend with the patient
looking at their eyes, you know, testing
them in various areas, the communication
that occurs in transferring say the
therapeutic plan or instructions for the
next week or two to that patient. It's
the also the idea that when you document
the care,
we know that that ambient listening by
AI can document the care as well, if not
better, when properly implemented,
>> right?
>> Better than that actual caregiver. Now,
think of the possibilities that can come
from that. The note that goes to the
patient can also be modified and written
in a way that that patient can
understand it and is meaningful to them.
is not just seeing the physician's note,
but seeing a customized summary of their
visit.
If there is a referral to a specialist,
the information from that referral could
be prioritized based upon the specialty
of that referred physician. So that the
most important details about that
patient are not buried somewhere in the
note but are right at the top because we
know a surgeon needs to know xyz about
the patient but less about some other
things. Right? For example, we might
it'd be very important to know the
patient's
some labs on a particular patient who's
going undergoing say a hip replacement,
but maybe their cholesterol level isn't
as important as their clotting factors
or the hemoglobin. And it can we can
make sure that those factors are right
up front and initially seen and that
also impacts care and improves the
quality of the care while at the same
time addressing the issue of the
physician burnout. I
>> I love that. Is there are there things
that you think we could do specifically
to really kind of lean in on what you're
saying? Make sure that the AI is
supporting rather than replacing the
human connection in medicine because I
think that's an area where probably is
the most uncomfortable for us across the
across the industry as we're thinking
about how do we use AI and do it in a
way that's meaningful.
>> Well, that goes back to the idea of
clinical AI.
Now we can do great things with AI in
terms of drug discovery, clinical trials
and I can go in details on some of those
but the challenge in using clinical eye
is in the idea of using it as a
therapeutic or diagnostic tool.
>> Right? The problem here is that if you
do not set up the workflow correctly and
you go ahead and implement that AI, you
have the risk of getting into automation
bias where the physician sees the AI
recommendation. They're busy. They're
distracted. Oh, by the way, physicians,
nurses, and other caregivers are human
beings. They are going to get
distracted. They are going to miss
things. We all miss things and make
errors. If you have automation bias,
it'll just go okay, okay, okay. We know
that AI can elucidate, can make up
things, provide misinformation. Without
that human chat, we have a problem. Now,
how do we address that? Well, we could
create AI that goes ahead and looks at
the output from the AI and monitors
that. Um, and there are other
surveillance tools we need to put in
place. So, it's actually multifaceted.
Let's make sure the workflow work is
correct. So the physician is part of the
process and we try our best in the
design to avoid the automation bias.
Second is we have some type of tool
whether it's AI or AI and some other
additional algorithm that works to check
on what the results are from the AI from
the physician's plan. And the third
thing is let's set up surveillance tool.
Let's go ahead and monitor how we're
doing with these things on a regular
basis and look for things that are out
of line that may be wrong and that way
we can work to correct them. Correct
them in terms of the workflow processes
and correct them in terms of the
artificial intelligence. That that
brings up an interesting concept because
I think when we talk about things like
surveillance, that word has negative
connotations probably that come to
people's mind. It gets big brotherish.
uh you're you're going to monitor me and
babysit everything that I do. I went to
medical school. I I mean I know what I'm
doing and your your technology is going
to be looking over my shoulder. Is that
what you're telling me? I mean I think
that's an interesting conversation
because I think we're
this is a bit different from a cultural
adjustment standpoint um for anybody
who's going to be measured this way. But
I think it's incred incredibly important
for the reasons that you said. I mean,
human nature is such that eventually, no
matter what our intentions are, we can
get comfortable and complacent over time
because 99% of the time it's right or
perception we have is it's always right.
I don't think I have to worry about it
anymore. Uh I think the the ability to
measure and I think that how I think
about it is if uh Dr. shaken is spending
on average 3 minutes reviewing the post
visit summary and this Hutchkins guy is
barely spending 30 seconds. Do we have
something that flags that this, you
know, somebody needs to come and talk to
that Hutchkins guy that he's clearly not
being attentive to it and he's putting
himself and his organization at risk. Uh
it's it seems seems like a little bit
more than people probably are accustomed
to thinking about, but I think it's
really important for the reasons that
you said. I mean, human nature is human
nature. I don't know how we short
circuit that. Well, Chris, maybe that
Hutchkins guy knows something that the
chicken guy doesn't know about and the
Hutchkins guy spending 30 seconds
instead of the 3 minutes and it's not
only much more efficient, but also then
has extra time to spend with that
patient. We don't know whether the
Hutchin guy or the Chaken guy is doing
the right thing. But let me give you
this model. If you go back
>> 40 years,
>> the chance of you dying in an airplane
crash
>> Mhm.
>> was 10, 20, 50, 100 times greater than
it is today.
>> Right.
>> Why is that? The reason is is because
the pilots who initially said, "Hey, I'm
the captain.
You can't tell me what to do. They
learned over time. That is the wrong
model. You have to have crew crew
resource management, which means the
captain, the co-pilot, and other people
on the aircraft all have a right to
intervene. Now, I'll give you an
example. What we do in healthcare, we
have a checklist
in the O. And anybody in the O who
thinks that something is not going
correct can stop the the beginning of
the surgery and ask them to recheck it
or to question it. That's the mindset we
have to have in healthcare, which is if
I'm looking at how you're doing, I'm not
looking to punish you. Now, I'll talk
about that in a second. We're not
looking to punish you. What we're
looking to do is to make sure that
you're within the parameters what we
expect. And oh by the way, we might
discover something that you're doing
that we should have everybody else do
cuz it's better. Fortunately, what how
surveillance is used today, particularly
in the forprofit
um hedge fundowned venture fund
organization,
it's taking you nurse four minutes to
spend the time on the phone with the
patient. You got to cut it down to 3
minutes and 45 seconds.
If any of you know a nurse, if any of
you are a nurse, you know that is not
the way you work. And doctors don't want
to work that way either. The most
important person in the room when you're
seeing a patient is the patient. You
went to medical school, nursing school,
PT school, or you joined health care as
an intake person with no medical
training, but you did it because you're
committed to that cause. That's what's
most important. We can make it more
efficient within the humanistic uh using
humans and and get them to do the right
thing, but we're not here to punish them
for time. We're here to identify the
best ways to do things and encourage
them to do the best for their patients.
>> Thank you for explaining that cuz I
think it's just a really important thing
that we have to get people to
understand. If if we don't put these in
place as we're starting to deploy, we're
definitely going to go in a in a
direction that's very very dangerous.
Uh, thank you for that. I want to get
into some things that are maybe a little
bit more difficult to wrap. Well, for me
it's a little more difficult to wrap my
head around in terms of use, the types
of use cases we can be comfortable with,
but you're right about predictive
diagnostics, decision support, and
workflow automation. Which of these will
be the most disruptive to current
medical practice? Do you think?
>> Um, we've evolved in using electronic
health records, right? I think that we
would be able to utilize these tools in
ways that could be incredibly beneficial
to patients. But what we need to do is
we have to involve the clinical people
in the design at least of the workflow
and the output and the surveillance
tools. We have to gain their trust in
utilizing them. And you know, let's not
forget about the patient. they should
have a voice in what they want to how
they want to use the AI in terms of
receiving say messages and summaries and
such. It has to be a holistic approach
to understand this this piece
>> and the and let's not decide what we're
going to do
>> before we've collected all the
information from everybody.
>> Right? How and the other thing is if you
want to fail in a hospital, what you
should do is implement something without
asking the nurses what you should do.
Okay? That's what you need to do. So
don't do that. Involve everyone, include
everyone, understand it, and then
implement it and tell people what you're
trying to accomplish.
>> Where can listeners find your book,
follow your work, or invite you to speak
further about this important topic? Uh,
we've only scratched the surface. Um,
but I know our listeners have have
gotten a ton of really great insight and
I I think you're going to need to make
it available. Tell them right where they
can get it because I think they're
they're going to be excited to read.
Well, you can find everything about me
at barrychen.com.
Uh, and in there you will you can have
some fun. Not only you can read about my
book, you can order a deluxe signed copy
there that I'll sign and if you want to
put a little message in to you and that
I can mail out to you. Um, it's also
available on Amazon and Barnes & Noble,
but obviously I can't sign them there.
Um, the second the second thing is what
I created was a little chatbot. Two
different types of chat bots. One of
them is you can text in it and that'll
appear on the the homepage as well as
there's a little menu here. You can go
to that and you can ask me questions.
But what I specifically did is if you
ask me what the weather's going to be in
your town next week, it'll specifically
say to you, "It's not my database and
I've been instructed not to
hallucinate." So, I've made a point of
doing that. The second one is I also
created one where you could actually
quote unquote call me. You hit the
little call button, you can ask the same
question, it'll respond back to you in
my cloned voice. So, it's just a little
fun way how to use AI. And um I have a
lot of uh uh information on my website,
barrychen.com, but of course, you know,
feel free to reach out to me using that
site. And please connect with me on
LinkedIn. Um it's barrychen.com/ln
and that'll uh link you up to LinkedIn
and my page and we can connect.
Right
now
[music]
>> [music]